Finding aid for the George H. Forsyth papers.
Bentley Historical Library
- Michigan-Princeton-Alexandria Expeditions to Saint Catherine's Monastery (Mount Sinai, Egypt), 1940-2012; 1954-1999
  The Michigan-Princeton-Alexandria Expeditions to Saint Catherine's Monastery (Mount Sinai, Egypt) series comprises the bulk of the collection. This series is arranged into five subseries: Correspondence, Travel Preparations, Field Work, Visual Materials, and Publication Activities. The Michigan-Princeton-Alexandria Expeditions are typically referred to as "Mt. Sinai" and occurred in four campaigns in 1958, 1960, 1963, and 1965. Materials of particular note include correspondence with Kurt Weitzmann, of Princeton University who co-led the expeditions, and Fred Anderegg, UM director of photography; trip preparatory materials such as equipment lists and medical supply information; field notebooks (two volumes); full-scale architectural drawings of the monastery and surrounding fortress, which were cataloged during Ilene's posthumous publication efforts (Box 9); and extensive repurposed source material, such as photographs, negatives, drawings, and field notes, reproduced and annotated for various publication activities. This material is described more fully at the subseries level.
  - Correspondence
    - 1957-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Anderegg, Fred, 1972-1975 (Box 7)
    - Mainstone, Rowland, 1967-1970 (Box 7)
    - Official correspondence, 1957-1973 (Box 7)
    - Pending unsolved problems, references etc., 1963-1979 (Box 7)
    - Scholarly correspondence, 1961-1987 (Box 7)
    - Shanks, Hershel, 1978 (Box 7)
      (Editor of The Biblical Archaeology Review.)
  - Travel Preparations
    - Expenses, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Clothing and equipment lists, 1957-1965 (Box 4)
    - Medical supply information, 1954-1965; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Official letter of introduction from U-M President Harlan Hatcher, 1960-1963 (Box 4)
    - Passport Ilene Forsyth, 1958-1961 (Box 4)
    - Religious documents, 1940-1960 (Box 4)
    - Trip correspondence, 1958 (Box 4)
      (Includes correspondence with Aziz Atiya.)
  - Field Work
    - Church field notes and drawings, 1963-1967 (Box 9)
    - Field Notebooks
      - Volume I, 1956-1968 (Box 4)
      - Volume II, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
    - Ilene's notes on church ceiling beams, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Le monastère de-Sainte-Catherine du Mont Sinaī par m. H. L. Rābino, 1938 (Box 9)
      (Forsyth's copy with annotations, 1956.)
    - Masonry notes and analysis, 1963-1967 (Box 9)
    - Radiocarbon dating, 1974-1981 (Box 7)
      (British Museum C-14 tests.)
    - Roof analysis, 1961-1991 (Box 8)
      (Includes correspondence.)
    - Total review of field notebook I, 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Unidentified notes, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Visual Materials
    - Drawings
      - Capitals in the nave-drawings, negatives, and reproductions, 1969; 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Cataloged Drawings
        (Forsyth's unpublished drawings of St. Catherine's Monastery. Cataloged by Ilene Forsyth and Lois Drewer, circa 1990s. Corresponding catalog in Box 9.)
        - Drawings 601-653 (Folder 8)
          (vellum)
        - Drawing 602, 1 tubes (Tube 1)
        - Drawings 625-650 (Folder 9)
          (paper)
        - Unidentified drawings (Folder 10)
      - Church details, 1960s (Box 8)
      - Fortress and chapel walls, circa 1960-1981 (Box 8)
      - Fortress south terrains, circa 1960-1981 (Box 8)
        (Includes notes and photographs.)
      - Original and photo-reproductions of drawings, circa 1960-1995; 5 folders (Box 24)
        (Includes original and reproductions of drawings with substantial annotations, keys, and notes.)
    - Photographs and negatives
      - Approach to mountain, 1987 (Box 8)
      - Berry survey of fortress
        - Notes, 1965 (Box 8)
        - Photographs for Berry survey, 1963; undated (Box 8)
      - Chapel, 1964; undated (Box 9)
        (Includes various shots inside/outside building.)
      - Church beams, 1970 (Box 8)
        (Foliate and sea creatures.)
      - Contact prints, 1956-1960; 30 rolls (in 1 box), 1 folder (Box 23)
      - Details
        - Beams over nave, inscriptions, 1968 (Box 8)
        - Bulls and goat, hare and hounds, undated (Box 8)
        - Crosses, 1987 (Box 8)
        - Mosaic in main apse, 1981 (Box 9)
          (Before and after cleaning.)
      - Doors, 1968; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Fire, 1980-1989; Includes slides. (Box 8)
      - Fortress views marked for publication, circa 1963-1978 (Folder 6)
      - Fortress walls (North, South, East, West), undated (Box 8)
      - Ilene's file, 1958-1963; undated (Box 8)
      - Infrared views of Mt. Sinai, undated (Folder 7)
      - Mango excavation, 1957 (Box 9)
      - Panorama sepia prints, 1963-1975 (Box 8)
      - Photographs for various publications, 1963-1985; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Photographs for U-M Press use, 1956 (Box 9)
      - Various images, 1960-1963; Negatives. (Box 8)
  - Publication Activities
    The Publication Activities subseries includes materials created by George Forsyth resulting in articles, exhibitions, a monograph executed during his life, and materials created and culled together by Ilene Forsyth posthumously. This subseries is comprised of correspondence with publishers including the University of Michigan Press, Dumbarton Oaks Papers, and Princeton University Press; annotated manuscripts and chapter drafts; two annotated galley proofs of The Monastery of Saint Catherine at Mount Sinai: the church and fortress of Justinian / Plates published with Kurt Weitzmann, Ihor Ševčenko, and Fred Anderegg (Box 14); and notes, drawings, and photographs reproduced for publication activities. Forsyth made detailed notes on photographs, scraps of paper, and envelopes during his continued analyses of his field notes and other source materials. The processing archivist transcribed existing folder titles or created titles based on information from envelopes, and where appropriate envelopes were kept with file contents to preserve Forsyth's notes.
    George Forsyth died prior to completing the publication of his landmark drawings of Saint Catherine's Monastery (Mount Sinai, Egypt). Publication efforts were continued posthumously by his wife, Dr. Ilene H. Forsyth, an art historian and professor at the University of Michigan. Her extensive efforts to publish George's work are documented is approximately three linear feet of manuscripts, correspondence, topical files, and a catalog of drawings, 1995-1997, located in Box 9.
    - Correspondence
      - Fan mail, 1964-1973 (Box 5)
      - Fawzi, Fakharani, 1973-1981 (Box 5)
      - General correspondence, 1964-1969; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Grossmann, Peter, 1982-1989 (Box 7)
      - Tsafrir, Yoram, 1979 (Box 5)
      - Weitzmann, Kurt, 1977-1986 (Box 5)
    - Dumbarton Oaks Papers
      - Annotated offprint of "The Monastery of St. Catherine at Mount Sinai: The Church and Fortress of Justinian", 1967-1968 (Box 7)
      - NASA satellite view of Sinai peninsula, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Photographs and reproductions for article, 1968; 1990 (Box 8)
      - Rejected travel note from Dumbarton Oaks Papers, 1957 (Box 7)
        (Includes photographs and correspondence.)
      - Revisions, 1988 (Box 9)
        (Draft of volume III in Princeton D.O.P. series, not published.)
      - Symposium on Justinian and Eastern Christendom, 1961-1970; 2 folders (Box 9)
        (Hosted by Dumbarton Oaks Center for Byzantine Studies. Includes correspondence, notes, and handwritten lecture text.)
    - Exhibitions
      - "Fortress of Faith" exhibit at U-M Kelsey Museum, 1978 (Box 7)
        (Photographs by Fred Anderegg.)
      - Sinai exhibit at Princeton University, 1958-1960; 1977 (Box 7)
      - Department of Art & Archaeology Sinai exhibit, Princeton University, 2006
    - Ilene Forsyth Posthumous Publication Efforts
      - Additional photographs, 1996 (Box 11)
      - Annotated drafts (multiple versions)
        - Introduction, 1998-1999; 4 folders (Box 10)
          (Includes various other chapters.)
        - Index, 1995-1998 (Box 10)
        - Outer walls of the monastery, 1996 (Box 10)
        - Selected annotations, working copies, 1998-1999 (Box 10)
      - Bibliography
        - Annotated version, 1998 (Box 10)
        - Included, 1998 (Box 9)
        - Not included, 1998 (Box 9)
        - Notes and excerpts, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Biographical notes on George, 1999 (Box 11)
      - Camels, 1985; 2000-2002 (Box 11)
      - Carbon 14 dating, 1997-2012 (Box 11)
      - Catalog of drawings, 1995-1997 (Box 9)
        (Index to George's drawings of the Monastery St. Catherine (Ov folders 8-10).)
      - Computer, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence
        - Blai, 1995 (Box 11)
        - Project related, 1995-1999 (Box 10)
          (Primarily between Ilene and Lois Drewer; also includes biography of George by Ilene.)
      - Color prints of Sinai for Kelsey Museum, 2004 (Box 9)
        (Includes 2 slides of Forsyth drawings.)
      - Drawings catalog "as found", 1995 (Box 11)
      - Drawing index Lisa's work, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Dunn-Blue photo-reproductions, 1997 (Box 11)
      - Exhibitions, 1998-2003 (Box 11)
      - Field notes list of diagrams, 1995-1997 (Box 11)
      - Field notes transcriptions, August 1995
      - Field notes transcriptions (revised), December 1995 (Box 11)
      - Footnotes of west towers, 1995; undated (Box 10)
      - Getty conservation, 2002 (Box 11)
      - Holger A. Klein publications, 2002-2005 (Box 11)
      - Ihor Sevcenko publication on Sinai doors, 1996 (Box 11)
      - Inventories, 1997-1998; 4 folders (Box 10)
        (Includes lists of George's field notebooks, correspondence, photographs, drawings, and other source material photocopies with annotations.)
      - John Elsner (Byzantine), 1999-2000 (Box 11)
      - Kariye Camii (Turkey) field notebook, 2003-2007 (Box 11)
        (Information on the field notebook's exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art.)
      - Kelsey, 2010 (Box 11)
      - Key to symbols and abbreviations, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Lois Drewer, 1992-1999; 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 11)
      - Newspaper clippings re: Sinai, 1996 (Box 11)
      - Notes of interpretations of George's work, 1995-1997 (Box 11)
      - Notes on drawings
        - 1997 (Box 11)
        - 1996
      - Notes on recent publications, 1990-1998 (Box 11)
      - Obituaries
        - 1993-2006 (Box 11)
        - Hawkins, Ernest, 1993 (Box 11)
        - Weitzman, Kurt, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
      - Old views compiled by Ilene, 1998; 2 folders (Box 9)
        (Images (photographs and reproductions) of St. Catherine's Monastery.)
      - Outline and notes, 1998-1999 (Box 10)
      - Printed materials, 1933-1985; undated; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Recent Sinai related literature, 1985-2006; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Recent travelers to Sinai, 1999-2000 (Box 11)
        (Correspondence.)
      - Red Monastery (Sohag, Egypt), 2012 (Box 11)
      - Thomas Matthews, 1979-1997 (Box 11)
        (Includes correspondence to George.)
      - Summary, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Synthesis, circa 1990s (Box 10)
        (Notes compiled from George's files.)
      - Xeroxed images, 1996-1998 (Box 10)
        (Copies of photographs labeled and annotated.)
    - John Galley book: Sinai and the Monastery of St. Catherine, 1978-1981 (Box 7)
      (Includes correspondence and chapter drafts.)
    - Lecture notes and talks, 1954-1964; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Monastery of Saint Catherine at Mount Sinai: the church and fortress of Justinian / Plates. By George H. Forsyth and Kurt Weitzmann, with Ihor Ševčenko and Fred Anderegg
      (Published by University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (1973). May also include drafts and materials for a second volume (never published) in this series.)
      - Contents and chapter introductions, 1988 (Box 7)
      - Forward and introduction "early versions", 1964 (Box 7)
      - Galley proofs, circa 1972-1989; 2 volumes (in one box) (Box 14)
        (Heavily annotated. Labeled "Working Copy I" and "Working Copy II.")
      - Manuscript drafts, 1963-1967; 6 folders (Box 7)
        (Various chapters heavily edited.)
      - Proposed title page proof for volume II, 1962 (Box 7)
        (Includes Kurt Weitzmann's letter of acceptance and "Agreement between the University of Michigan and Princeton University concerning the Sinai Expedition.")
    - Notes, drawings, photographs, and negatives, 1960s-1970s; 6 folders (Box 5)
      (Materials may relate to various publication efforts.)
    - Richard Pococke's Observations on Egypt annotated, circa 1960s (Box 9)
    - University of Michigan Press
      (Primarily regarding the publication of Volume I.)
      - Book reviews, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence
        - 1961-1968 (Box 5)
        - 1962-1966 (Box 5)
        - 1967-1971 (Box 5)
        - 1972-1975 (Box 5)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - Meeting notes, 1966; 1977-1978 (Box 5)
      - Memorandum of Agreement, 1967 (Box 5)
      - Publicity and author questionnaire, 1968-1974 (Box 5)
The University of Michigan, History of Art Department Visual Resource Collection (VRC) holds the following collection of related material: Sinai Archives Collection. Parts of this collection are digitized and available online by searching the terms "Forsyth" and "Sinai" here at: https://quod.lib.umich.edu/h/hart